太阳是我们太阳系的超级大国
The Sun is the superpower of our Solar System,
一座高热核反应堆 巨大的爆炸喷发
a thermonuclear blast furnace, erupting with massive explosions.
它能将相当于珠穆朗玛峰那样质量的聚合物
It can be the same amount of mass as mount Everest
从太阳抛出进入太空
coming out from the Sun and flying out into space.
我们安全地在9300万英哩外看着太阳的狂怒
At 93 million miles away it would seem that we are safe from the Sun's wrath.
然而我们？
But, are we?
特别是在当今关心的是
It matters, especially in modern times,
太阳在干什么？
what the Sun is doing?
太阳旋转的中心
From the center of the Sun, as it rotates around,
宛如"死亡之区"
is the "kill zone".
一些专家预测了现代太阳活动
With some experts predicting the most violent outbreak of solar activity
最剧烈的爆发
in modern history.
这比任何时候都来的重要 去了解
it never been more important to understand
太阳的秘密
the secrets of the Sun.
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://www.hdcmct.com
历史频道·宇宙第一季第1集 太阳的秘密
影片压制:暮云春树 字幕来源：射手网 调校：TIAN@CMCT 招募Q号: 76846146
宇宙中有数十亿颗恒星
There are billions of stars in the Universe
但只有一颗宇宙近邻主宰着我们:
but one alone dominates our cosmic neighborhood:
太阳
the Sun.
它是一颗地狱般的星球 大部分是氢和氦
It's an infernal sphere, of mostly hydrogen and helium,
高温成为等离子体 在数百万度下燃烧
superheated into a plasma, that burns at millions of degrees.
其表面猛烈地爆发
Its surface reages with violent explosions,
抛出致命的辐射风暴进入数百万英哩的太空
as it spews out storms of deadly radiation, millions of miles into space.
我们的太阳是称做黄矮星一类的恒星
Our Sun is a type of star known as a yellow dwarf.
黄是因为其表面的颜色
Yellow because of the colour of its surface,
而矮是因为它是一颗小恒星
and dwarf because it's small for a star.
但小是相对的
But small is relative.
在它的边界范围内可以放进一百万个地球
Within its boundaries, you could fit one million earths.
在我们的太阳系根本没有比太阳更大的星体了
In our Solar System, there's simply no bigger star than the Sun.
在数百万英哩范围内 它是巨大的天体炸弹
At a million miles across, it's a massive celestial blockbuster.
太阳实在是相当巨大
The Sun is really pretty huge.
它支配着我们的太阳系
It dominates our Solar System.
不仅是太阳系里最大的星体
Not only is the bigger star of the Solar system,
而且是太阳系里唯一的恒星
it's the only star in the Solar System.
它的四周围绕着较小的物体
It's sorrounded by a bunch a smaller stuff,
我们称之为行星 慧星和卫星
that we call planets and comets and moons.
然而太阳是我们的恒星
But the Sun is our star.
我们的恒星是热和能源巨大的来源
Our star is an enormous source of heat and energy.
有10000华氏度(约5560摄氏度)的表面温度
It has a surface temperature of 10,000 Farenheit.
产生3 8万亿亿兆瓦特的能源
And generates 380 billion billion megawatts of power.
人类在此显得微不足道
This dwarfs anything on the human scale.
内华达州的胡佛水坝仅发电280兆瓦特
Hoover Dam in Nevada only generates 280 megawatts.
太阳一秒钟制造的能源
In one second the Sun churns out more energy
比所有人类文明社会用过的能源还要多
than has been used in all of human civilization.
所有的能量在眨眼之间
All that power in the blink of an eye.
无法相信的是太阳已经以这种方式燃烧了数十亿年
Incredibly, it's been burning this way for billions of years.
早期的科学家没有搞明白
Early astronomers didn't quite understand how
太阳为什么能够在这么长的时期内产生如此多的能量
the Sun could generate so much energy for that long a period of time.
真正的第一个谜是太阳怎样产生能量的
That was the first mistery, it was really how the Sun generates its energy.
在19世纪早期
In the early nineteenth century,
科学家假设太阳就像地球上的火
scientists assumed that the Sun worked just like any fire on Earth,
来自像煤这样的燃料慢慢地燃烧
that there was a source of fuel, perhaps coal, that was slowly burning away.
然而这个理论的一个严重的问题:
But that was a serious problem with this theory:
我的面前有一堆火
I've got a fire in front of me here,
如果我想维持燃烧 就要不停地给加入木头
if I want it to keep burning, I have to keep adding wood to it.
这火大概只能维持一个小时 除非加进更多的木头
This fire will last maybe an hour, unless I add some more wood.
现在假如我有像太阳那样大的一堆木头
Now, if I had a pile of the wood the size of the whole Sun,
同时某种程度上有足够的氧气来燃烧
and somehow enough oxygen to burn it,
只能维持大约5000到6000年的燃烧
it would only take about 5000 or 6000 years to burn out.
那是一个长的时间 但还不够长得足够支撑地球的生命
That's a long time, but it's not long enough to sustain life on Earth.
在20世纪早期
By the early twentieth century,
地球岩石和化石的碳-14年代测定证实
carbon dating of Earth rocks and fossils had proven
太阳已经以足够维持生命的温度存在了
that the Sun was in existence and at temperatures warm enough to sustain life
不是几千年而是30亿年
not for thousands of years, but for 3 billion.
如果你想烧一把维持这么长时间的火
If you wanted to build a fire that would last that long,
你就需要72万亿捆的柴火
you would need 72 trillion cords of firewood.
那是地球上每一个男人 女人和孩子各12000捆
That's 12,000 cords for each man, woman and child on the planet.
显然必须有其它的一些作业方式
Clearly, there had to be some other process,
是地球上未知的动力 供应着太阳
unknow on Earth, that was powering the Sun.
1929年科学家在掌握氢弹核燃料后
In the 1920's scientists found the answer to the puzzle,
找到了谜题的答案
in a process that would later be harnessed to fuel the hydrogen bomb.
核聚变
Nuclear fusion.
聚变发生在原子被高速打碎
Fusion occurs when atoms are smashed together at a high rate of speed
并逐个重组聚合 为了达到目的
and literally fused. To get this to happen,
条件都必须恰到好处
conditions have to be just right.
这发生了一些相互作用--两个质子 每个质子各带
For any interaction to happen, these two protons, each has
一个正电荷 因此相互排斥
a positive electric charge and so they would repell each other,
你想让它们充分靠近
so you got to get them close enough together.
要做到这一点则需要加热 这意味着
And to do that, it's got to be hot, which means
粒子运动速度加快 足够密集 彼此撞击和
the particles are moving fast, and dense enough that they, they hit each other
相互足够地靠近而实现聚合
and they can get close enough together so they actually fuse.
太阳的核心是个完美的核聚变反应堆
The core of the Sun is the perfect cauldron for nuclear fusion.
它是太阳系中最热的地方 有2700万华氏度(1500万摄氏度)
It's the hottest place in the Solar System, at a sweltering 27 milion Degrees Fahrenheit.
而且它也非常的密集
And it's also incredibly dense.
它是如此的密 其密度是铅的10倍
It's so dense, it's ten times the density of lead,
你会认为那么高的密度会是一个固体 但不是
and you would think at that density it should be a solid, but it's not
而是高热状态下等离子体
because it's so hot that remains a plasma.
如果你把气体加热到足够的高温
If you heat a gas to high enough temperatures
电子脱离了原子 像漂浮在汤里的漂浮物
electrons fall off of the atoms and they float around in the soup.
因此它有着不同于气体的性质
And so it has behavior that's different from what a gas would do,
我们有一个不同的名字来描述叫做等离子
hence we have a different word for it, we call it plasma.
要真正明白太阳核里进行着什么
To truly understand what goes on in the core of the Sun,
你必须以某种方式去想像 简直是"不可思议"
you have to find some way to imagine the almost "unimaginable"
除了研究太阳以外我还玩撞球
In addition to studying the Sun, I also play pool
太阳中有着无数粒子
and the Sun is a place where there are billions of particles,
相互冲撞 作用
colliding and interacting with each other.
在一个不可思议的规模内 它和宇宙撞球桌没什麽区别
And it is really not unlike a cosmic pool table, on an unimaginable scale.
很难打中一个球 这无所谓
It doesn't matter how hard you hit a ball.
实际上那个球击中另一个聚合在一起
You would never hit hard enough to actually
不会很困难
fuse that ball together with another ball.
而在有如此高的压力 密度的太阳核里
But there's so much pressure and such high density at the core of the Sun,
两个物体可轻易地相互碰撞 融合在一起
that two objects impacting each other, will actually fuse.
在太阳里这些物体是氢原子
In the Sun, these objects are hydrogen atoms,
在巨大的压力下飞撞在一起 形成氦原子
flung together by immense pressure, to form helium atoms.
在这个聚合过程中 产生的原子(氦)比初始原子(等离子氢)的质量
In this fusion process, the resulting atom is slightly less massive
稍微小一点
than the ones they created it.
缺少的质量作为能源释放了
The missing mass is given off as energy.
每一秒钟太阳内部有6亿吨氢聚合
Each second, inside the Sun, 600 million tons of hydrogen are fused
产生5 95亿吨氦
into 595 million tons of helium.
缺失的500万吨质量转换成了能量
That five million tons of mass lost in the process is converted into energy
等于10亿个百万吨级的氢弹
equal to one billion one megaton hydrogen bombs.
那是在每一秒内
That's every second.
当你注意到宇宙间
When you look out into the cosmos,
获得免费的能源最大的收益的途径
the process that gives you the highest return of energy
在于像太阳那样的恒星中心进行
for free, is what goes on in the centers of stars like the Sun.
现在我们知道了太阳是靠核聚变产生能量的
So, we now know that the Sun is powered by nuclear fusion.
它是我们知道的唯一燃料
It's the only fuel we know,
能够承担太阳燃烧长期提供能源支撑
that can sustain the burning in the Sun long enough
地球的生命达数十亿年
to sustain life on Earth, billions of years.
阳光
Sunlight.
对生活是如此的重要 我们一秒钟都无法离开它
It's so central to life that we don't often give it a second thought.
然而光从那里到这里原来是个难以置信的故事
But how light gets from there to here, turns out to be an incredible story.
聚变产生的能量送出太阳的核心
The energy created in the fusion process is carried out of the core
是靠光和热的粒子叫做光子
by particles of light and heat called photons.
光子把太阳的温暖带给地球
They are what bring the warming rays of the Sun to Earth.
为了来到我们地球 这些来自我们最近的恒星的光子
To reach our planet, these glowing travellers from our nearest star
必须首先经过太阳各层 漫长艰辛的道路
must first take a long winding road through all the layers of the Sun,
就像但丁到地狱各层去一样
like Dante journeying through the levels of Hell.
首先光子进入185000英哩长的辐射区
First, a photon enters the 185,000 mile-thick radiative zone.
区内的道路是如此的崎岖
The region is so densely packed
光子经常游荡进入其它粒子里面
that the photon constantly bumps into other particles,
如氢和氦原子里
like hydrogen and helium atoms.
它以无序曲折的模式向外挣扎
It struggles outward in a chaotic zigzag
这种模式科学家称之为"随机游动"
pattern that scientists call the "random walk"
光子如果没有一而再 再而三的相互作用是无法逃逸的
A photon can't escape without interacting over and over and over again,
它被原子吸收和重新接纳
getting absorbed by atoms and reemitted
能够被吸收和重新接纳数百万次
and it can be absorbed and reemitted millions of times.
随着密度减小光子可以更远地离开太阳中心
As the density decreases as you get further up in the Sun,
变得较为宽松 相互作用减少
it becomes easier and the collisions and the interactions are less.
当到达距离太阳表面130000英哩时
When it finally reaches to within 130,000 miles of the surface,
光子进入了对流层
the photon enters the convective zone,
速度突然加快
and the pace suddenly quickens.
被一种沸腾卷的
It's carried upwards by a kind of boiling,
巨大的气柱裹着 以每小时几百英哩卷出去
riding along in huge columns of gas at hundreds of miles an hour,
到达太阳表面只要10天功夫
taking only ten days to emerge on the solar surface.
随着光子通过太阳稀薄的大气层
The incredible journey is almost over
难以置信的旅程差不多就结束了
as the photon lifts off through the wispy gasses of the solar atmosphere.
从那只须8分钟
From there, it takes only 8 minutes
穿过9300万英哩的空间
for it to zip across 93 million miles of space
到达我们地球
to our planet.
无法相信在阳光真正到达地球时
Incredibly, by the time sunlight actually reaches Earth,
光子已经存在了
it's already been in existence
成千上万年 甚至百万年
for hundreds of thousands, if not millions, of years.
对太阳来说百万年实在是微不足道
For the Sun even a million years is a small blip in time.
完美的日落
The simple perfect disc of a sunset,
掩饰着我们的恒星长期狂暴的历史
belies the long, violent history of our star.
它是诞生在数十亿年前的火球
It is a ball of fire spawned billions of years ago
产生在一次被认为是超新星的巨大爆发里
in a massive explosion known as a supernova.
在那次大爆发后那颗远比太阳大的恒星破碎了
After this titanic explosion where a star much larger than the Sun exploded,
留下了比太阳系大许多倍 巨大的气体云
there would have been a huge cloud of gas many times larger than the Solar System.
在这个非常巨大的云里 崩塌的小碎片
And small nods of material would have gradually coalesced
逐渐地合并
in this very large cloud.
大约50亿年前
About five billion years ago,
大爆炸后大约100亿年
some ten billion years after the Big Bang
科学家认为我们的宇宙坍缩
that scientists believe kickstarted our Universe,
在万有引力作用下开始坍缩
this cloud started to collapse under the pull of gravity.
我们的太阳系可能产生于这样一个
Our Solar System probably arose from one such nod
气体相互牵引自由结合的碎片
of self gravitating gas that pulled itself together
逐渐自己环绕着转起来
and gradually spun itself up
它收缩起来就像溜冰者在自旋时收起双臂一样
as it pulled in, like a skater pulling her arms in during a spin,
直到太阳形成和各种行星收缩围绕着它
until the star and the various planets coalesced around it.
最后当太阳足够致密 开始
Ultimately, when the star was dense enough, it would have turned on
氢聚变点火 开始发热发光
fusion, started glowing and giving off sunlight.
为什么科学家认为太阳是从超新星的灰烬里诞生的呢？
Why do scientists believe the Sun was born from the ashes of a supernova?
这明显地在我们脚下展现出来
The evidence lies beneath our feet.
复杂的重元素
Complex heavy elements
如我们从地球上开采出来用于发电厂的燃料的铀
like the uranium we mine from the Earth to fuel our nuclear powerplants,
是无法在太阳上制造出来的
could not have been forged in the Sun,
太阳那样大小的恒星没有足够的热量
there is simply not enough heat in a star of that size
去产生任何比铁重的元素
to create elements any heavier than iron.
重元素--像铀
Heavy elements, like uranium,
只能产生在灾难性的宇宙爆炸中
can only be created in a catastrophic cosmic explosion.
在太阳系里地球和其它行星
Earth and the other planets in the Solar System
的形成 不同于构成太阳的气体物质
formed out of the same nod of gas that produced the Sun.
在这里太阳占有了99%的物质
In this process the Sun hoarded 99% of the mass.
这就意味着它是宇宙中我们邻近的最大的物体
This means it's the biggest object in our celestial neighborhood,
有最强的引力
with the strongest gravitational pull.
这就是其它物体围绕着它旋转的原因
That's why everything else revolves around it.
相对于其它行星地球争得了对于太阳的特殊位置
Of all the planets, Earth earned a privileged place in relation to the Sun.
如果太靠近太阳
If we were closer in,
大海将沸腾蒸发 地面会热得足以把铅融化
our oceans would boil away and the ground would be hot enough to melt lead.
如果太远我们的星球将变成冰冻的废墟
If we were farther out, our planet would be a frozen wasteland.
所以就像Goldylocks和三头熊
It's a sort of like Goldylocks and the Three Bears,
不太热也不太冷 正好
not too hot, not too cold, it's just right.
这里大约距离太阳9300万英哩远
Here we are at about 93 million miles away
能在这里我们幸福 幸运
from the Sun and we're happy to be here, we're lucky to be here.
感觉上说我们这的环境不错
In some sense we're here because it's the right circumstance for us to be here.
地球是太阳系里刚刚正好的地方
Earth may be in just the right place in the Solar System,
但也有缺陷 容易成为太阳发怒的靶子
but we're also close enough to the Sun to be a target of its fury.
每年数以千计的爆发晃动着我们的太阳
Thousands of mammoth explosions rock our Sun every year.
你可能认为这种爆发来自太阳中心的核反应
You might expect this explosive force to come from nuclear reactions in the core,
事实上驱使太阳猛烈爆发的是磁力
but in reality what drives all outbursts of solar violence is magnetism.
自从太阳像固体那样自转后
Since Earth rotates as a solid,
我们的磁场就很简单 有两个磁极--北极和南极
our magnetic field is simple, we have two poles: North and South.
这就是罗盘能在地球上指示方向的原因
This is what makes a compass so useful for finding your way around the planet.
但是想像一下每100-1000万年两极替换
But imagine if instead of two poles you had 1 to 10 million.
这是太阳引起的
This is what happens on the Sun.
太阳的磁场
The Sun's magnetic field
是靠引力结合在一起的一张复杂的网
is a tangled web because even though it's held together by gravity,
等离子无法均匀的旋转
the plasma doesn't rotate evenly.
等离子在赤道
Plasma at the equator
旋转一圈平均为25个地球日
rotates once every 25 Earth days,
而在两极旋转一圈就需要35天
while plasma at the poles takes roughly 35 days to circle once.
太阳被我们称为差动自转
The Sun has what we call differential rotation.
所有的等离子
You have all this plasma
它旋转啊旋转
that is really turning and turning
造成磁场扭曲
and that causes magnetic field lines to become twisted
内部纠缠在一块
and intertwined and mixed up.
尽管看不见磁力线
Although magnetic field lines are invisible,
但我们知道它存在于太阳
we know they exist on the Sun
其特征被称为"冕环"和"日珥"
by looking at features called "coronal loops" and "prominences"
一路上升到太阳大气层
rising up into the solar atmosphere.
就像金属屑排列在一个简单磁场里
Just as metal shavings line up in the presence of a simple magnet,
这些等离子的回路
these loops of plasma
从下面完美地描绘了支持它们的磁构造
perfectly outline the magnetic structures that support them from below.
这些等离子拱桥是如此的高和宽大
These plasma arches are so tall and wide
可以把木星那样大的行星放进去穿过它
that you could slide a planet as big as Jupiter right through them.
有时磁场会扭曲在太阳大气中的等离子
Sometimes magnetic fields can twist plasma
进入称为"通量绳"的宏伟的螺旋体
in the Sun's atmosphere into majestic helical shapes called "flux ropes"
磁场通量绳有点苗条
A magnetic flux rope is sort of like a slinky.
磁力线被包裹在螺旋结构里许多次
The magnetic field line is wrapped around many times in a helical structure,
一旦有了高度盘旋的磁力线后
and when you have highly twisted magnetic field lines,
就储存了大量的磁能
it carries a lot of stored free magnetic energy,
有时甚至会自己缠绕在一起
and sometimes it will even kink in on itself
还能储存更多的磁能
which gives it even more stored magnetic free energy.
这些等离子红焰能持续几个星期或几个月
These plasma prominencies can last for weeks or months,
但是最后储存的能量会释放
but eventually the stored up energy has to be released,
质量会飞入太空
and the mass is flung off into space.
在太阳磁场最盘根错节的地方
Where the Sun's magnetic field is at its most twisted and complex,
保持着底下上来的热涌动
heat bubbling up from below is kept
物质的温度要低1000度
and the material is cooled by as much as 1000 degrees.
结果形成了黑斑
What results are relatively dark blemishes
在太阳表面称为"黑子".
on the solar surface called "sunspots"
黑子的暗只不过是对应着周围明亮的物质
Sunspots are only dark in relation to the bright material around them.
如果你能将其中一个放到空中
If you could somehow suspend one alone up in space,
它会比满月亮10倍
it would shine 10 times brighter than the full Moon.
这些明显的小斑点
These apparently tiny blemishes
实际上是等离子创造出来的 相当于整个地球大小
are actually plasma craters the size of the entire Earth.
伽利略是现代第一个观察太阳黑子的科学家
Galileo was one the first modern scientists to observe sunspots.
他使用望远镜把太阳的影像投射到纸上并描绘出来
Using a telescope he projected an image of the Sun onto paper and traced it.
他看到了斑点越过太阳表面
He realized that the blemishes were moving across the face of the star,
第一次指出太阳的旋转
which was the first indication that the Sun rotated.
不仅太阳在旋转
Not only does the Sun rotate,
而且一些黑子自身也会在太阳表面旋转
but sunspots themselves can actually spin like hurricanes on the solar surface.
此时黑子的磁力线变得非常的扭曲
And when they do, their magnetic field lines become extremely twisted.
扭曲的磁力线意味着更多的能量
Twisted magnetic field lines mean more energy
而更多的能量意味着潜在的大爆发
and more energy means the potential for huge eruptions.
想像下橡皮条就像磁力线
Think of a rubber band as magnetic field line.
如果你扭曲它 充分扭曲它 它就得到了所有的能量；
If you twist it, and you twist enough it's goin to have all that energy,
而当你放开它时 能量就释放出来
and when you let it go it's going to release.
如果你拆掉橡皮条就不会飞行
If you just take an untwisted rubber band and release it it's not going to fly.
当太阳黑子释放其磁能时
When a sunspot unleashes its magnetic energy,
就会在太阳系引发最激烈的爆发:
what results are the most colossal explosions in the Solar System:
太阳耀斑
solar flares.
单个耀斑会释放10亿兆顿当量的能量
A single flare releases as much as a billion megatons of energy.
等于地球上一百万座火山喷发
The combined power of a million volcanic eruptions on Earth.
它们看来是非常
They appear as these very
白色的区域是如此的明亮 这是因为其温度是如此的高
bright regions and they're so bright because the temperature is so high,
大约有1000万度 能持续几个小时
on the order of ten million degrees and they can last for hours.
能量是巨大的
But the energy is massive.
整个爆发
The whole explosion
等于数百万个核弹
is equivalent to millions of nuclear bombs
同时离开太阳表面
leaving the surface of the Sun all at once.
太阳耀斑不只是在太空爆发
Solar flares don't just explode out into space.
还能集中高能粒子
They also funnel high energy particles
掉进太阳色球层
down to a layer of the Sun called the cromosphere,
在那很快地传递能量
where they quickly transfer their energy
就像母球撞击台球桌上的色球
like a cue ball striking the rack in the game of billiards.
你有一个母球 事实上就像这些
So you have a cue ball, actually is like one of these
能量非常高的粒子是来自耀斑地区
very high energy particles coming from the flare region.
母球非常快地撞击8号球进洞
The cue ball smacks very quickly into the 8-ball rack,
一旦击中头球
and once it impacts that head ball,
就会传递那个能量
it's going to transfer that energy
给后面的球
to the balls behind it and then
它们就会散开 这是因为能量传递给了所有的球
they will all fly out because the energy is transferred to all of them.
如果一个大的耀斑一次充分发出足够的能量
If a large flare shoots enough high energy particles at once,
奇异的事情开始产生
strange things start to happen.
这是真实的连续记录
This is actual footage
关于日震的
of a sunquake.
在1998年
In 1998
一个太阳耀斑产生在日冕
there was a solar flare up in the
非常强大 等离子飞速下降
corona that was so powerful that the material flying down
回太阳的表面
toward the surface of the Sun
竟然停止在太阳表面
actually slapped the surface and
造成涟漪在那扩展开来
caused ripples to spread out from there.
尽管看起来那里有个涟漪
While thay may look like ripples on a pot,
实际上是两英哩高的
these are actually waves two miles high
极速运动
travelling at a maximum velocity of
达到每小时25万英哩的速度
250 thousand miles per hour.
1998年的日震
The 1998 sunquake
震级达到里氏11 3级
would have measured an 11.3 on the Richter scale.
强度等于100万倍于
More than one million times stronger
1989年
than the 1989 earthquake that
旧金山的那次地震
shook San Francisco.
为了更多的晃动太阳表面
In order to shake the surface of the Sun that much,
太阳耀斑必须释放大量的能量
the solar flare had to release a colossal amount of energy.
换算过来几乎等于
It turns out it's almost the same amount of energy
用炸药覆盖地球整个表面
as if you cover the entire landmass of the Earth with dinamite,
一码(0 91米)厚
about a yard thick.
一次爆炸
And set it all off at once.
那些爆发很大
So, these explosions are not small.
在太阳上地震不是唯一的天灾
Earthquakes aren't the only natural disasters with equivalents on the Sun.
耀斑还能引起太阳的海啸
A flare can also kick-off a solar tsunami,
当太阳大气层里的等离子波
as waves of plasma in the Sun's atmosphere rock it up
以每小时70万英哩的速度跃起
at 700 thousand miles per hour,
散布到太阳的整个表面
spreading around the entire face of the star
在几小时之内
in a matter of hours.
而日震和海啸
While sunquakes and solar tsunamis
没给地球造成危害
pose no danger to Earth,
耀斑猛烈的活动
the violent action of a flare
经常会引发危险的爆发
frequently triggers dangerous eruptions
被称为日冕物质抛射 简称CMEs
called coronal mass ejections, or CMEs.
在一个CME里
In a CME
来自耀斑的能量消失在一团
energy from a flare flings a blob of
高电荷辐射等离子
highly charged radioactive plasma
冲出太阳的大气层
out of the solar atmosphere.
日冕物质抛射
Coronal mass ejections
其范围和速度 卷曲状地
range in speeds, but they can occur
快速地
as quick as
每秒800-900英哩速度
800-900 miles per second,
极端的快速
which is extremely fast and they
并抛出大量的物质
expell a massive amount of material.
它抛出的物质的大小 这么说吧相当于珠穆朗玛峰
It can be the same amount of mass as, say, mount Everest,
离开太阳
coming out from the Sun and
飞进太空
flying out into space.
当高热高辐射的等离子团离开
Where does this blob of superheated radioactive
太阳后会到哪里去呢？
plasma go when it leaves the Sun?
有时在太空里无害地航行
Sometimes it sails out harmlessly into space.
其他时候可能会接近我们的家园
Other times it may head closer to home.
来自太阳的日冕物质抛射
Coronal mass ejections from the Sun
也许是你从未听说过的最大的危害
are perhaps the most dangerous threat you've never heard of.
亦称为太阳风暴
Also known as solar storms,
抛出大量超重粒子
they hurl a large masses of supercharged particles
越过9300万英哩空间
across 93 million miles of space.
大部分经过几天从太阳到地球
Most take several days to travel from the Sun to the Earth,
一部分飞越太阳系
but some rocket across the Solar System
高于每小时600万英哩的速度
at up to 6 million miles an hour,
到达地球不足16个小时
reaching our planet in less than 16 hours.
这些风暴能够引起外大气层的电流
These storms can induce currents in the outer atmosphere
轰击人造卫星和旷野的输电线
knocking out satellites and cross-country power grids
带着电压
and carry the potential to
就像许多重炮手那样轰击基础设施
wreak just as much havoc on our infrastructure
如同飓风或龙卷风
as a hurricane or a tornado.
但地球上谁在留意
But who on Earth is keeping an eye
这个宇宙风潜在的危害呢？
on this potentially hazardous cosmic blasts?
这是
This is the headquarters
美国国家海洋与大气管理局的总部
of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration,
为美国政府提供气象服务
home to the US government's national weather service.
他们的日常预报 观察和警告
Their daily forecasts, watches and warnings
是我们地球每天生活的基本信息
are essential information for everyday life on our planet.
然而有一个很少有人知道的预报员团体在这里工作
But there is a lesser known group of forecasters working here
一个特殊的部门称为"太空环境中心"
in a special division called "The Space Environment Center"
我们主要的工作是监控太阳
Out primary job is to monitor the Sun
提供警报 观察和警告
and put out the alerts, watches and warnings
关于太阳活动方面的
for solar activity.
早安 欢迎来听取简报
Good morning and welcome to our 10 briefing.
这有一个东半球未知的像是耀斑的东西
We have one long duration C-flare from the east limb,
可能是日冕物质抛射
that's a possible CME.
我们没有质子但有电子
We have not had protons but we have had electrons.
一件事你们要注意 这个区域
One thing you notice is that this region
太阳上活动停止的漂亮地方
produced all the activity in december
在未来几个星期里可能会停下你的项目
so things might be picking up here in the next couple of weeks.
这些太空预报员
These space forecasters
高度戒备对付太阳风暴
are on high alert for solar storms
它可能破坏地球上的生命
that might disrupt life on Earth.
太阳风暴会产生带电粒子
Solar storm clouds are made up of charged particles,
它们被磁场牵制
so they are initially diverted around the planet
在地球周围
by our magnetic field,
就像围绕着船头的波浪
just like waves breaking around the bow of a boat.
它转出去是非常重要的
That turns out to be very important
因为如果直接撞击外大气层
because if it impacted the outer atmosphere directly,
将把小部分大气撞进太空
it would knock little bits of the atmosphere off into space.
火星为什么没有大气的原因之一
One reason why Mars doesn't have an atmosphere
就是没有一个内在的强大的磁场
is that it doesn't have a strong internal magnetic field.
慢慢地经过了
And so gradually over
数百万可能数十亿年
millions or maybe billions of years,
大气逐渐被撞进了太空
the atmosphere was gradually knocked off into space
被那太阳风
by the influence of the solar wind
和日冕物质抛射掠过以前的火星
and by the CMEs that came past the planet.
然而我们的磁场不是科幻电影里的理想的磁力场
But our magnetic field is not the perfect force field of sci-fi movies.
有些粒子可能穿透它
Some particles can penetrate it
电离上部的大气
charging up the upper atmosphere.
太阳风暴甚至会弯曲和打破磁力线
Solar storms will even bend and break the magnetic field lines
在地球的远方
on the far side of the Earth,
让带电粒子沿着磁力线落进
allowing charged particles to zip back down the field lines
北极和南极
toward the north and south poles.
非常强大的风暴会扭曲磁场
Extremely powerful storms distort the magnetic field
进一步甚至误导跨越
even futher, inducing electric currents
大陆的电流
that span the continents.
当这发生时 像长途输电这样的技术
When this happens technology like long-distance powerlines,
会出现超载
can become overloaded.
这是因为破坏了线路两端的变压器
It can cause damage to trasformers at either end of the line.
事实上在1989年
In fact, in 1989
加拿大魁北克省大部分地区
most of the canadian province of Quebec
回到了灯火管制年代 那是因为变压器
blacked-out because a transformer was blown out
被一次太阳发怒吹坏了
by a solar event.
如果我们被那个风暴打中
If we have that storm that hits our
通讯系统 打中
communication system and hits our
我们的公司和所有我们依赖的东西
our power companies and all these things that we depend on,
那就会产生各种各样的混乱
there is all kinds of chaos that can lay out there.
假如电力操作人员有时间去对付
If power operators have time to react,
就能够减少电流
thay can reduce the current
送上电线
being sent over their wires
避免灾难
and avert disaster.
人造卫星操作员也能够
Satellite operators can also
随着正确的警告
prepare for the onslaught
准备对付冲击
with proper warning.
当一个大的太空风暴来临时
When there's a big space storm coming,
我们实际上会让一些卫星进入睡眠状态
they'll actually put some of their satellites to sleep,
所以风暴
so that the storm
不会引起电路短路
doesn't cause an electrical short
或者用其它方式干掉卫星
or otherwise somehow knock out the satellite.
所以预警时间越长越好
So the more warning time they have, the better.
我们不会去航行
We wouldn't go sailing
除非我们知道会是什么样的天气
unless we knew what the weather is going to be.
同样的我们有一个大的系统
Similarly when we have a large system
像电力系统或电话网路会被
like a power system or a telephone grid that can be affected
天气和太空影响
by the weather in space,
就需要了解天气会是怎样的
we need to know what the weather is going to be
这样我们能够试着减轻它的影响
so that we can try and mitigate it.
太阳风暴同样也会使用于航天器的
Solar storms can also disrupt high frequency radiocommunications
高频无线通讯中断
used by aircraft.
1980年
In the 1980's
空军一号送里根总统出访中国
Airforce One was transporting president Reagan on a trip to China
就被太阳风暴击中过
when a solar storm struck.
所有的通讯丧失了
All communications were lost
几个小时
for several hours,
事实上造成了
effectively severing the head of
美国政府群龙无首
the United States government.
这种紧急情况就像碰到坏天气
The urgency is just like our ERS weather.
一方面我们得到龙卷风警报
When we have a tornado warning
知道要告知公众
we know the urgency to get that out to the public
让公众知道那是个意外
to let the people know that this is happening.
太空气像是同样的情况
The same thing is with space weather.
利用这个信息
Users of this information
让大家了解现在什么是他们需要了解的
need to know it and they need to know it now.
几个小时后我们将经历一次日冕物质抛射
Just a few hours back we experienced a coronal mass ejection.
我们希望看到这个耀斑出去了
We wanna see where this blast is going out,
接着就可以测量它以及
and then we can measure that and see
看它从太阳到地球要多长时间
how long it might take from that to reach the Earth from the Sun.
我们看到巨大的爆发
We're seeing a very huge explosion
抛出的物质
of material that's coming out
如果你看这个小的图像
and if you look at this small image here,
这里的太阳被遮住了
here's the Sun that's covered up,
看那物质被抛进了太空
and look at the mass that's being thrown out into space.
很大 非常大
So it's huge, very huge.
因为磁力线从北极和南极流出
Because magnetic field lines emanate from the North and South Poles,
来自太阳风暴的能量轻易地靠近这些区域
energy from solar storms has easy access to those regions.
出于这个原因专家担心飞机上的乘客
For that reason, experts worry that airplane passengers
在强大的风暴爆发期间飞越两极
flying over the Poles during a powerful storm,
可能会暴露在辐射中
might be exposed to harmful levels of radiation,
也许相当于100次X光胸透
perhaps are those equal to a hundred chest x-rays.
这不是我们想要管的乱七八糟的事 因为永远不知道
It's not something that we want to mess around with, because we never know
当那辐射可能突然变得
when that radiation might all of a sudden become
更加激烈 而此时天上正好有飞机飞行
a lot more intense while there's an airplane in the sky.
来自太阳辐射的威胁只是多了一个理由
The threat from solar radiation is just one more reason
让科学家密切关注太阳
for scientists to keep a close watch on our Sun.
太阳的活动特别是在当代 事关紧要
It matters, especially in modern times, what the Sun is doing.
地球不是安全岛
Earth is not an island.
我们是太阳系活动的参与者
We are participant in the activities of the Solar System.
太阳黑子会引发更剧烈的太阳风暴
Sunspots are the triggers for more severe solar storms,
所以预报员小心地跟踪它
so forecasters track them carefully,
在它们越过太阳表面时
as they rotate across the surface of the Sun.
地点 地点 地点 我们全过程地看到来自太阳的日冕物质抛射
Location, location, location. We see CMEs all the time from the Sun.
在中心旋转时大量的物质抛射从太阳的背后转出来
A lot of them, as the center is rotated around, are from the backside of the Sun.
由于不会面对地球 所以很少关注
That would not be face towards the Earth, so that would be less of a concern.
随着太阳的旋转 那个活动的区域逐渐靠近中心
As the Sun rotates around and that active region gets more into the center of the disk,
对我们来说那是我们要关注的
looking at us, then that's when we would be concerned with.
随着它的自转太阳的中心如同杀伤区
From the center of the Sun, as it rotates around, is the kill zone.
随着黑子旋转开始直接面对地球
As the sunspot rotates around and begins to face directly at Earth,
此时我们开始被风暴困扰了
that's when we really have to worry about a storm.
如果此时风暴停止
If a big storm leaves off then,
会直接瞄准地球 风暴的全部的影响力会冲击地球
it can aim directly at Earth, and the full force of the storm slams into the planet.
就像猎枪瞄准靶子
It's like a shotgun aiming at a target.
射击造成许多死亡
The more dead on the shot,
将可能会造成严重的损害
the more likely serious damage will be inflicted.
巨大的威胁还来自惊人的美景
With great danger also comes astonishing beauty.
太阳风暴会产生宏伟的行星的光表演
Solar storms generate majestic planetary lightshows.
五彩缤纷的微光幕帘叫做极光
The shimmering courtains of colour called the Aurora.
极光就像霓虹灯活动在巨大的空中
Auroras work like neon signs, on an enormous scale.
在霓虹灯里电流引导带电粒子进入充满气体的管子
In a neon sign, electricity introduces charged particles into a gas-filled tube.
气体里的粒子跳跃起来 开始发光
The particles in the gas are excited and start to glow.
如果管子里只有氖气 就发红光
If the tube has only neon inside, it will glow red.
放进其它气体如氩 就会产生完整的色谱带
By adding other gases, like argon, a whole range of colors can be produced.
霓虹灯是靠管子里的电流驱动的
The neon sign is driven by the electric field inside the tube,
而极光的驱动是靠磁场和来自太阳的能量
whereas the Auroras are actually driven by the magnetic field and energy from the Sun.
由于太阳风暴里活跃的粒子
As the energetic particles in a solar storm
沿着地球的磁场流入两极
stream along Earth's magnetic field towards the Poles,
激发大气里的元素使其发光
they excite elements in our atmosphere causing them to glow.
氧分子发出绿或红色
Oxygen molecules emit a green or red color.
氮分子发出粉色 兰色和紫色
And nytrogen emits pinks, blues and violets.
虽然这些恐怖的光通常被限定在两极
While these ghostly lights are usually confined to the Poles,
极端强烈的太阳风暴也会驱使它们靠近赤道
extremely strong solar storms can drive them closer to the Equator.
1859年一个巨大的太阳耀斑引发的磁暴
In 1859 a geomagnetic storm ignited by a huge solar flare
在远在罗马这样的南方制造了极光
created Auroras as far south as Rome.
1859年的风暴是一个罕见的大事件
The 1859 storm was an unusually powerful event
被称为"完美太阳风暴"
that some have called "the perfect solar storm"
1859年的风暴告诉了我们一点点太阳的所作所为
The 1859 storm taught us a little something about what the Sun can do.
风暴是如此的激烈 组合是如此的完美
The storm was so intense and the alignment was so perfect,
地球的天然屏障简直不堪一击
that it simply overwhelmed Earth's natural defenses.
一个巨大的太阳耀斑在太阳上喷发
A huge solar flare erupts on the surface of the Sun.
9300万英哩的路程才不到一天
Less than a day later and 93 million miles away,
横跨地球的通讯线缆开始爆出火花
the wires the carry communications across the Earth, begin to spark.
折磨着全世界
Business grinds to a halt worldwide
当野火被小小的闪光点燃时
as wild fires are ignited by the smoldering lines.
在同一时刻五颜六色的极光照亮了遍布全球的城市
At the same time, colorful Auroras light up the skies of cities around the globe.
地球正好被完美太阳风暴造访
Earth has just been visited by the perfect solar storm.
太阳激起这难以置信的耀斑
The Sun kicked up this just incredible solar flare
大量能量冲向地球
and a massive amount of energy headed towards Earth.
这个风暴不仅是两个有记录的 不仅是最大的一个
Not only was this storm one of the two most powerul on record,
而且还是最快的一个
it was also one of the fastest.
黑子的喷射很快到达地球
Ejecting from a sunspot aimed directly at Earth,
它快速地从太阳到地球还不到18小时
it raced from the Sun to our planet in less than 18 hours.
如今用最快的宇宙飞船到太阳也要化几年功夫
Now, it takes a really fast rocketship years to get to the Sun.
这个风暴--带电粒子团
This storm, this cloud of electrified particles,
到达这里不到一天时间
managed to get here in less than a day.
快得难以置信
That's incredibly fast.
幸运的是完美太阳风暴发生在1859年
Fortunately, the perfect solar storm took place in 1859,
当时受攻击的地球上的科技还只是电报
when the only technology vulnerable to the onslaught was the telegraph.
自从进入了高科技时代
Since the era in wich we've become dependant on high technology,
我们等着看另一个完美太阳风暴
we've yet to see another perfect solar storm.
问题是它还会发生吗？
The question remains: Could it happen again?
若是发生了一个像那个的风暴？会有另一个完美风暴吗？
What if we have another one like that? Can we have another perfect storm?
我说会的 无须质疑
I'd say yes we can, there's no doubt about that.
今天 对我们的影响 相比较1859年可能 毁灭性的
The effects that would be on us today compared to 1859 could be devastating.
对地球的 对通讯的影响
The effects on Earth and on our communication systems,
我们并不确切知道 那是惊心动魄的一部分
we don't exactly know. That's the scary part.
有可能我们的现代技术遭到打击
It's likely that our modern technologies would be battered
就像海边的狂风中的房屋一样
like beachfront houses during a hurricane.
想像一下如果我们失去了移动电话
Imagine if we lost all the satellites that relay cellphone calls,
电视信号和银行传递依赖的卫星
television signals and bank transactions.
如果发生在同一时间
And what if at the same time,
电力供应的故障一连串的雪崩 把所有地方带进黑暗几个小时或几个星期
the failure of power grids cascaded whole regions into darkness for hours, or weeks.
如果这些基本服务不能很快恢复
If these essential services couldn't be restored quickly,
将会造成混乱
chaos wouldn't be far behind.
会给社会 给生活在地球上的男女老少
It would definitely be a ripple effect upon society
带来可怕的后果
and every man and woman and child that lives on this Earth.
太阳风暴像飓风那样难以预报
Solar storms can be as hard to predict as hurricanes.
当下一个完美风暴来临时 预报员缺少预报技术
While forecasters lack the technology to foretell the next pefect storm,
他们知道打击终将到来
they do know that one would be more likely to hit
在匆匆看过太阳11年的黑子周期后
at the peek of the Sun's eleven-year sunspot cycle.
太阳每11年磁场的方向变化后
What happens is the Sun reverses the direction of its magnetic field
会发生什么？
every eleven years.
所以在22年里它总是变过去 回过来
So in 22 years it reverses and comes back to where it was.
当我们接近每11年的逆转时
As we near the reversal every eleven years,
黑子的数量增加 太阳活动达到峰值
the number of sunspots increases and there's a spike in solar activity.
我们称那周期为"太阳活动最大期"
We call that period solar maximum
而那些是5年分布周期
and those periods are interspersed about 5 years apart
是从太阳活动最大期里分离出来的
from periods we call solar minimum.
所以这11年太阳来回折腾
So you have this eleven year back and forth
有时非常惊人
between the Sun being sometimes very ferocious,
变得疯狂 一直就像独立日的烟火
and it goes crazy and it's like the 4th of July with fireworks all the time.
接着开始缓慢停止
And then it starts to ramp down
几年后会安静下来直到变成
and for a few years it gets quieter until we get to
一个小点 像个灿烂过的爆竹
a low point where there is a firecracker now and then but not a lot going on.
就像飓风季节 太阳活动最大期在强度上会变化
Just like hurricane seasons, solar maximums vary in intensity.
太阳会产生比其它时候更强的风暴
Some produce many more powerful storms than others.
尽管在一般的太阳活动最小期 科学家也要小心地观察它
Although we're currently at solar minimum, scientists are watching carefully
留意下一次最大的太阳能可能释放的时间
to see what mayhem the next solar max might unleash.
最近的一次太阳活动最大期大约在2001年
The last solar maximum was in about 2001
所以下一次可能在2012年 但预报也会不一样
and so the next one ought to be about 2012, but there are different predictions.
整个太阳物理学家焦急地等待着
The whole field of solar physicists is basically waiting with bated breath
将要实际发生的情况
to see what actually happens.
他们对将要发生的事情有一些大的分歧
There are some wildly divergent opinions on what's gonna happen.
某个团队认为下一个太阳周期
One group is suggesting that this next solar cycle
会是现代最强的
could be the strongest in modern times.
如果那些预报准确的话地球将走上疯狂之路
If those predictions are correct, Earth could be in for a wild ride.
我们将不得不重复1859年的痛苦
We might have to worry about a repeat of the 1859 event.
如果今天发生的话将造成深重的灾难
If that would happen today it would wreak untold damage.
在和平时期里 我们需要认识许多关于太阳
We're gonna learn a whole lot about what can happen
对现代科技产生的影响
to modern technology when the Sun bows its top.
太阳喷发的众多暴行发生在
Much of the violence in the Sun erupts here,
地狱般的 外部大气层中的日冕里
in the hellish outer atmosphere known as the corona.
这个区域长期以来就是太阳的一大秘密
This region has long held one of the great solar mysteries.
因为即使距太阳高热核心有50万英哩
Because even though it's half a million miles from the heat-generating core,
还是有数百万度的高温
it burns at millions of degrees.
这似乎违背物理定律
This seems to violate the very laws of physics.
那非常奇怪 这里有只温度计
That's very strange. I have a thermometer here.
如果我把温度计靠近火
If I hold the thermometer close to the fire,
有很高的读数
it reads a very high reading.
探针测出超过200度
Where the probe is right now it's over 200 degrees.
然而如果把探针稍微离开点
And if I pull the probe out a little farther from the fire,
你瞧 下降了90度左右
ok, it drops down to about 90 degrees.
下一步把它伸进中心 温度更低了
Now, the farther I get from the center, the cooler it gets.
太阳大气日冕的温度猛增 同核心一样热
In the atmosphere, the corona of the Sun, the temperature soars as hot as the core.
那犹如 我是说距我背后很远的地方
That's as if, I were to say, well, way off behind me there,
火堆里传出的热量和火堆里一样
the heat from the fire is as hot as the fire itself,
甚至可以传得更远
even though it's very far from the fire.
是什么造成了日冕的高温呢？
What force could possibly cause the superheating of the corona?
答案会让你震惊
The answer will rock you.
凶狠的日冕以数百万度的温度呼啸
The hellish solar corona rages at millions of degrees.
几个世纪以来科学家们很困惑
For centuries scientists have been baffled
怎么距离日心这么远的地方
how anything so far from the Sun's core
仍然会有这么高的温度
could still burn so hot.
最近随着改进的人造卫星发回的太阳表面的近距离观察
Recently, as improved satellites offered a closer view of the solar surface,
线索开始显现
clues began to emerge.
在日冕下面太阳表面简直是个火海
Below the corona the Sun's surface is literally boiling.
原因是整个太阳表面
The reason is that the entire surface of the Sun
覆盖着对流单元 热物质从太阳里面出来
is covered with convection cells, hot material from the inside of the Sun,
上升穿越到达表面 发光冷却
that rises up through, reaches the surface, cools off by glowing,
发出阳光然后沉下去
giving off sunlight and then sinks back down.
升起的每个泡泡有德克萨斯州那么大
Each bubble of material that comes up is about the size of Texas.
它散布在表面冷却并在5分钟里下沉下去
It spreads out across the surface, cools off and sinks down in 5 minutes.
所以这是一个非常剧烈的过程
So, that's a tremendously violent process
那发生在 不夸张地 几乎所有地方
that's happening in, literally, almost a million places
覆盖整个太阳表面 日以继夜
over the entire surface of the Sun, all the time around the clock, 24/7.
沸腾不仅仅剧烈而且非常喧闹
This boiling is not only violent, it's also extremely loud.
太阳是非常喧闹的地方
The Sun is a tremendously loud place.
若想像一下 整个太阳表面覆盖的
If you could imagine covering the entire surface of the Sun
吵闹者 和你曾去光临的摇滚音乐会相比一样的歇斯底里
with speakers being driven as hard as the loudest rock concert you've ever been to,
太阳表面就这么闹得慌
that would be comparable to how loud it really is on the surface of the Sun.
太阳表面的搅动甚至会产生声能
The Sun's churning surface creates enough sound energy
给日冕供给数百万度热量
to superheat the corona to millions of degrees.
科学家相信这些声波和能量的集合物
Scientists believe that a combination of these sound waves and energy
是缘于太阳磁场的作用
from the Sun's magnetic field
是日冕产生极端高温的原因
is responsible for the extreme temperatures found in the corona.
从地球上观察日冕的唯一机会
The only time you can actually see the corona from Earth
是在太阳系中最耀眼的高潮时刻--
is at the climax of one of the most dazzling displays in the Solar System,
-日全食
a total solar eclipse.
在科学家搞明白之前
Before scientists understood them,
这些严肃令人振奋的事情只被当成恐惧
these awe inspiring events instilled only fear.
古代的中国人认为是龙吃掉了太阳
【非龙也!乃天狗食日!是风趣的比喻 东方敏锐的智慧!】
The ancient Chinese believed that a dragon was devouring the Sun.
那么是日食真的发生了什么？
So what's really happening in a solar eclipse?
简单的道理是月亮运转遮住了太阳
In simplest terms it's when the Moon blocks our view of the Sun.
想像一下你非常快乐的在看电影
Imagine that you're sitting in a movies watching very happily
荧幕上在放映 有人
something going on on the screen and then somebody
在你前面经过
in the row in front of you comes across
挡住了你的视线
and blocks your view.
在电影院里你不希望这种人
In a movie theater you might not want that person
挡在你的前面 然而
to come across in front of you, but at
在日食里我们非常欢迎月亮越过太阳
an eclipse we're very lucky to have the Moon come across the Sun,
非常希望它正好横过太阳的中间
and we're lucky to have it come right across the middle.
我们也非常庆幸 月亮(直径)虽然比太阳(直径)小400倍
We're also lucky that the Moon, although it's 400 times smaller than the Sun,
但也正好400倍靠近我们
is also 400 times closer to us.
这个宇宙的巧合意味着两个物体
This cosmic coincidence means that the two objects
刚好尺寸大小一样地挂在天空上
just happen to be the same apparent size in our sky,
正好一个可以完全遮住另外一个
which allows for one to completely block out the other.
这个奇妙的宇宙现象只发生在
This magnificent cosmic event only happens
月亮的轨道横穿过地球和太阳之间
when the path of the Moon intersects the line between the Earth and the Sun.
月亮的轨道有近5度的倾斜
The Moon's orbit is tilted slightly about 5 degrees.
如果不是的话 每个月都会有日食
If it wasn't we would have an eclipse every month.
那时我们会觉得无聊
And then we'd be bored,
但是我们觉得不无聊是因为大部分的月份
but we're not bored because most months
月亮的轨道在日地之间
the Moon goes above or below
的上方或下方
the place where the line goes from the Earth to the Sun.
不是每个月都有一次日全食
So instead of one every month we get a total eclipse
而是地球上的一些地方每1 5年才有一次
somewhere on Earth about once every year and a half.
当月亮挡在太阳前面时
As the Moon slides in front of the Sun,
把影子投在地球上
it casts a shadow onto the Earth.
外面的部分影子是模糊的
The outer part, where the shadow is fainter,
称为半影
is called the penumbra.
如果你站在半影扫过的区域里
If you're standing within the swath traced by the penumbra,
当它沿着地球表面移动时
as it moves along the Earth's surface,
你就只能看到日偏食
then you'll see only a partial eclipse.
然而进到里面黑影的部分
But travel to a spot within the path of the dark inner shadow,
叫做本影
called the umbra,
你将体验到日全食的雄伟
and you'll experience the majesty of a total eclipse.
假如你无法去日全食发生的地方 还有一个选择
There's another option if you can't travel to the path of totality,
那就在一个地方等足够的时间
wait in one place long enough
日全食会正好在你的头顶上的
and a total eclipse will pass right over your head
大约每300年一次
about once every 300 years.
太阳 我们太阳系的最明亮的恒星
The Sun, that shining star of our Solar System,
即出奇的美丽 但又是极度的残暴
is capable of both astonishing beauty and ferocious violence.
似乎无法使人相信
It seems impossible to believe,
它不会永恒生存
but it won't be around forever.
最终连太阳也必然灭亡
Eventually even the Sun must die.
太阳核的燃料数量是固定的
The Sun has a fixed amount of fuel in its core,
经过燃烧其速度是可以计算出来的
it is undergoing fusion at a rate that you can calculate.
有太阳使用燃料的速度
So here's the rate it's using its fuel,
有多少燃料
here's how much fuel you have,
通过简单的计算就可以表明太阳什么时候会灭亡
so it's a simple calculation to show when the Sun will die,
大概会在50亿年左右
and that's in about a five billion years.
是的 可惜太阳不会在大爆炸中走完一生
Well, unfortunately the Sun will not go out with a bang.
它太小了不会像超新星那样喷发
It's too small to erupt in a supernova.
不管怎样太阳会发生特别的情况
However stars do a peculiar thing,
最有可能是随着冷却会趋于白热
they're one of the few things around that get hotter as they cool off.
随着氢燃料的用尽 我们亲密的太阳会变冷
As it exhausts its hydrogen fuel, our nearest star will cool
在引力作用下逐渐崩塌
and gradually collapse under the force of gravity.
崩塌产生的能量会再次加热日核
Energy from this collapse will start heating up the core again
到数亿度 足够的温度开始使氦核点火
to hundreds of millions of degrees, hot enough to start burning helium.
在氦燃烧额外的加热中
Onto the extra heat of the helium burning,
太阳将膨胀成巨大的天体 称为红巨星
the star will expand into a monstrous orb called a red giant.
它是如此的庞大会吞没
It'll get so big it will engulf
整个轨道上的水星 金星和地球
the entire orbits of Mercury, Venus and Earth.
不可能再围绕着它
You don't want to be around for that.
你会希望"行星跳跃"轨道以提升安全度
You want to be planet-hopping your way to safety
在此发生之前
long before this happens.
在太阳膨胀时地球会稍微改变它的轨道
The Earth is likely to change its orbit slightly as the star expands,
所以我们不会被吞没
so that it won't be engulfed.
但是在讨论全球变暖时你不会想到这
Still, talking about global warming, you wouldn't want to be here.
太阳的外层会变得不稳定
The outer layers of our Sun will eventually become so unstable
会飞进太空
that they will fly off into space,
最后剩下地球般大小的日核
leaving behind a small core about the size of the Earth.
太阳的大部分会收缩
So remember we've shrunk most of the Sun,
由一百万英哩直径缩小到像地球(直径7918英哩)
which is a million miles across, to the size of the Earth which is
那样6000英哩跨度大小
more like 6000 miles across.
我们过去伟大的太阳慢慢地冷却为余烬
Our once great star reduced to a slowly cooling cinder.
地球上的生命将寿终正寝
Life as we know it on Earth will cease to exist.
那就是太阳的末日
And that is the death of the Sun.
所有这些对人类是个厄耗
All of this is bad news for the human race,
然而来看看光明的一面
but look on the bright side.
我们会有50亿年对这个灾难进行补救
We've got five billion years to prepare for this disaster.
现在人类沐浴在
For now, humanity basks in the glow of a Sun
全盛期的太阳辉光中
in the prime of its life.
科学家揭去了我们最亲密恒星的许多秘密
Science has uncovered many of the secrets of our nearest star,
但我们对这个美人依然要保持着敬畏
but we remain awed by its beauty,
谢谢观赏
Thanks For Viewing
而且要永远地提防着它的神谴
and ever more wary of its wrath.